<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
	xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
<channel>
<title>Phys.org: Astronomy News</title>
<link>http://phys.org/space-news/astronomy/</link>
<language>en-us</language> 
<description>Phys.org provides the latest news on astronomy, space, earth science and space exploration. </description>
<image>
    <url>http://cdn.phys.org/tmpl/v4/img/phys.org.140.png</url>
    <title>Phys.org</title>
    <link>http://phys.org/</link>
</image>
 <item>
     <title>Using 19th century technology to time travel to the stars</title>
     <description>In the late 19th century, astronomers developed the technique of capturing telescopic images of stars and galaxies on glass photographic plates. This allowed them to study the night sky in detail. Over 500,000 glass plate images taken from 1885 to 1992 are part of the Plate Stacks Collection of the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics (CfA), and is is the largest of its kind in the world.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346577263.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2015 09:10:01 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346577263</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/using19thcen.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Best view yet of dusty cloud passing galactic center black hole</title>
     <description>The best observations so far of the dusty gas cloud G2 confirm that it made its closest approach to the supermassive black hole at the centre of the Milky Way in May 2014 and has survived the experience. The new result from ESO's Very Large Telescope shows that the object appears not to have been significantly stretched. It is most likely to be a young star with a massive core that is still accreting material.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346579597.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2015 09:06:47 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346579597</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/bestviewyeto.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Supermassive black hole clears star-making gas from galaxy's core</title>
     <description>Many nearby galaxies blast huge, wide-angled outpourings of material from their center, ejecting enough gas and dust to build more than a thousand stars the size of our sun every year. Astronomers have sought the driving force behind these massive molecular outflows, and now a team led by University of Maryland scientists has found an answer.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346488389.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2015 14:00:08 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346488389</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/supermassive.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Automation offers big solution to big data in astronomy</title>
     <description>It's almost a rite of passage in physics and astronomy. Scientists spend years scrounging up money to build a fantastic new instrument. Then, when the long-awaited device finally approaches completion, the panic begins: How will they handle the torrent of data?</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346425308.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 14:15:17 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346425308</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/automationof.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Galactic &quot;rocket engine&quot; explains unusual stellar motion in galaxies</title>
     <description>A discovery by MPIA graduate student Athanasia Tsatsi has changed astronomers' understanding of how mergers of two galaxies can produce unusual stellar motion in the resulting elliptical galaxies, with the central region rotating in the direction opposite to that of the galaxy's other stars. Previously, such differences had been thought to be the result of an opposite (&quot;retrograde&quot;) orientation of the galaxies prior to their merger. Looking at a simulation of a galaxy merger, Tsatsi discovered a different way of bringing about such counter-rotating cores, which involve mass loss from the bodies of these galaxies acting as a primitive galactic &quot;rocket engine.&quot;</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346403477.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 09:00:01 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346403477</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/galacticrock.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Dwarf galaxy that reveals the history of the universe</title>
     <description>The first galaxies were formed some 13.3 billion years ago, mainly composed of hydrogen and helium, the primary elements that emerged from the Big Bang. Their study to date has been technically very challenging due to their great distance from us, but the observation of analogous galaxies in our vicinity has turned out to be an excellent shortcut.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346399299.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 07:20:01 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346399299</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/dwarfgalaxyt.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>NASA satellites catch 'growth spurt' from newborn protostar</title>
     <description>Using data from orbiting observatories, including NASA's Spitzer Space Telescope, and ground-based facilities, an international team of astronomers has discovered an outburst from a star thought to be in the earliest phase of its development. The eruption, scientists say, reveals a sudden accumulation of gas and dust by an exceptionally young protostar known as HOPS 383.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346399274.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 07:01:24 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346399274</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/7-nasasatellit.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Wandering Jupiter accounts for our unusual solar system</title>
     <description>Long before Mercury, Venus, Earth, and Mars formed, it seems that the inner solar system may have harbored a number of super-Earths—planets larger than Earth but smaller than Neptune. If so, those planets are long gone—broken up and fallen into the sun billions of years ago largely due to a great inward-and-then-outward journey that Jupiter made early in the solar system's history.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346334079.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 15:00:07 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346334079</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/oursolarsyst.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Chemical fingerprints of ancient supernovae found</title>
     <description>A Carnegie-based search of nearby galaxies for their oldest stars has uncovered two stars in the Sculptor dwarf galaxy that were born shortly after the galaxy formed, approximately 13 billion years ago. The unusual chemical content of the stars may have originated in a single supernova explosion from the first generation of Sculptor stars. The team, which includes Carnegie's Josh Simon, Ian Thompson, and Stephen Shectman, will publish their work in The Astrophysical Journal.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346332074.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 12:21:22 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346332074</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/chemicalfing.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Colliding stars explain enigmatic 17th century explosion</title>
     <description>New observations made with APEX and other telescopes reveal that the star that European astronomers saw appear in the sky in 1670 was not a nova, but a much rarer, violent breed of stellar collision. It was spectacular enough to be easily seen with the naked eye during its first outburst, but the traces it left were so faint that very careful analysis using submillimetre telescopes was needed before the mystery could finally be unravelled more than 340 years later. The results appear online in the journal Nature on 23 March 2015.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346328138.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 12:00:04 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346328138</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/collidingsta.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Image: Misshapen NGC 2936 galaxy</title>
     <description>What do you see in this image from the NASA/ESA Hubble Space Telescope: a porpoise or a penguin?</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346320887.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 09:14:53 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346320887</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/imagemisshap.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Measuring galaxy evolution with globular clusters</title>
     <description>Globular clusters are gravitationally bound ensembles of stars, as many as a million stars in some cases, grouped in roughly spherical clusters with diameters as small as only tens of light-years. Globular clusters are typically located in the outer regions (the halos) of galaxies; the Milky Way galaxy has about two hundred globular clusters orbiting it. Astronomers are interested in globular clusters in part because they are home to many of the oldest known stars, but also because of their locations in the halos.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346312389.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 07:20:01 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346312389</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/measuringgal.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>HAWC Observatory to study universe's most energetic phenomena</title>
     <description>Supernovae, neutron star collisions and active galactic nuclei are among the most energetic phenomena in the known universe. These violent explosions produce high-energy gamma rays and cosmic rays, which can easily travel large distances—making it possible to see objects and events far outside our own galaxy.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346078210.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2015 13:50:21 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346078210</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/1-hawcobservat.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Physicists seek answers on supermassive black holes with the next-gen X-ray telescope</title>
     <description>University of Waterloo Professor Brian McNamara along with two Canadian astronomers will be part of the science working group directing ASTRO-H, the Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency's (JAXA's) newest flagship x-ray astronomy observatory.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346075385.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2015 13:03:14 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346075385</guid>
     
</item>
<item>
     <title>Could the death star destroy a planet?</title>
     <description>In the movie Star Wars, the Darth Vader's Death Star destroyed a planet. Could this really happen?</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346062976.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2015 10:10:01 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346062976</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/couldthedeat.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Search for extraterrestrial intelligence extends to new realms</title>
     <description>Astronomers have expanded the search for extraterrestrial intelligence into a new realm with detectors tuned to infrared light. Their new instrument has just begun to scour the sky for messages from other worlds.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news346047443.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2015 05:17:38 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news346047443</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/searchforext.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Milky Way's center unveils supernova 'dust factory'</title>
     <description>Sifting through the center of the Milky Way galaxy, astronomers have made the first direct observations - using an infrared telescope aboard a modified Boeing 747 - of cosmic building-block dust resulting from an ancient supernova.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345994897.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 14:41:53 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345994897</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/550b18204f733.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Hubble explores the mysteries of UGC 8201</title>
     <description>The galaxy UGC 8201, captured here by the NASA/ESA Hubble Space Telescope, is a dwarf irregular galaxy, so called because of its small size and chaotic structure. It lies just under 15 million light-years away from us in the constellation of Draco (the Dragon). As with most dwarf galaxies it is a member of a larger group of galaxies. In this case UCG 8201 is part of the M81 galaxy group; this group is one of the closest neighbors to the Local Group of galaxies, which contains our galaxy, the Milky Way.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345968176.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 07:16:23 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345968176</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/hubbleexplor.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Vision quest: Curator catalogs the world's oldest telescopes</title>
     <description>You could say Marvin Bolt takes the long view.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345954118.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 03:40:02 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345954118</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/visionquestc.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>More than a million stars are forming in a mysterious dusty gas cloud in a nearby galaxy</title>
     <description>More than a million young stars are forming in a hot, dusty cloud of molecular gases in a tiny galaxy near our own, an international team of astronomers has discovered.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345909784.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 15:03:15 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345909784</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/morethanamil.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>The Milky Way's new companion galaxies</title>
     <description>When we think of cosmology, we often imagine the largest telescopes peering into the deepest space, collecting the feeble light from exploding stars or the first galaxies.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345887425.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 09:40:01 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345887425</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/themilkyways.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Mexico to inaugurate powerful new space observatory</title>
     <description>Perched atop a volcano in Mexico, a new generation observatory capable of detecting exploding stars, black holes and solar flares will begin operating this week, scientists said Tuesday.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345870621.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 04:30:04 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345870621</guid>
     
</item>
<item>
     <title>Planets in the habitable zone around most stars, calculate researchers</title>
     <description>Astronomers have discovered thousands of exoplanets in our galaxy, the Milky Way, using the Kepler satellite and many of them have multiple planets orbiting the host star. By analysing these planetary systems, researchers from the Australian National University and the Niels Bohr Institute in Copenhagen have calculated the probability for the number of stars in the Milky Way that might have planets in the habitable zone. The calculations show that billions of the stars in the Milky Way will have one to three planets in the habitable zone, where there is the potential for liquid water and where life could exist. The results are published in the scientific journal, Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345836427.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 01:00:01 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345836427</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/planetsinthe.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>New binocular nova discovered in Sagittarius</title>
     <description>Looks like the Sagittarius Teapot's got a new whistle. On March 15, John Seach of Chatsworth Island, NSW, Australia discovered a probable nova in the heart of the constellation using a DSLR camera and fast 50mm lens. Checks revealed no bright asteroid or variable star at the location. At the time, the new object glowed at the naked eye limit of magnitude +6, but a more recent observation by Japanese amateur Koichi Itagaki puts the star at magnitude +5.3, indicating it's still on the rise.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345803657.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2015 10:00:01 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345803657</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/newbinocular.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>&quot;Mini supernova&quot; explosion could have big impact</title>
     <description>In Hollywood blockbusters, explosions are often among the stars of the show. In space, explosions of actual stars are a focus for scientists who hope to better understand their births, lives, and deaths and how they interact with their surroundings.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345748316.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 18:15:08 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345748316</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/minisupernov.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Colorful life-form catalog will help discern if we are alone</title>
     <description>While looking for life on planets beyond our own solar system, a group of international scientists has created a colorful catalog containing reflection signatures of Earth life forms that might be found on planet surfaces throughout the cosmic hinterlands. The new database and research, published in the March 16 Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, gives humans a better chance to learn if we are not alone.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345718898.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 15:00:05 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345718898</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/5506e2198b711.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>A second minor planet may possess Saturn-like rings</title>
     <description>There are only five bodies in our solar system that are known to bear rings. The most obvious is the planet Saturn; to a lesser extent, rings of gas and dust also encircle Jupiter, Uranus, and Neptune. The fifth member of this haloed group is Chariklo, one of a class of minor planets called centaurs: small, rocky bodies that possess qualities of both asteroids and comets.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345723928.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 11:25:39 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345723928</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/solarsystem.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Hubble Source Catalog: One-stop shopping for astronomers</title>
     <description>Astronomers at the Space Telescope Science Institute and the Johns Hopkins University, both in Baltimore, Maryland, have created a new master catalog of astronomical objects called the Hubble Source Catalog. The catalog provides one-stop shopping for measurements of objects observed with NASA's Hubble Space Telescope.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345538434.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2015 07:54:07 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345538434</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/hubblesource.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>Cosmic bumps on cosmic ripples</title>
     <description>In 1969, the astrophysicists Rashid Sunyaev and Yakov Zel'dovich realized that the then recently discovered cosmic microwave background radiation (CMBR) would be distorted by hot cosmic gas. Hot electrons in the intergalactic medium preferentially scatter the light in one direction, causing a change in the brightness of the CMBR towards clusters of galaxies where electrons should be abundant. They showed that the effect would reveal the large-scale structure of the universe, the nature of the CMBR, cosmological parameters like the Hubble constant, and physical conditions in galaxy clusters.</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345456596.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 09:50:01 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345456596</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2015/cosmicbumpso.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>
<item>
     <title>How do we know dark matter exists?</title>
     <description>Dark matter can't be seen or detected by any of our instruments, so how do we know it really exists?</description>
     <link>http://phys.org/news345455129.html</link>
     <category>Astronomy &amp; Space - Astronomy</category>
     <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 09:10:01 EDT</pubDate>
     <guid isPermaLink="false">news345455129</guid>
     <media:thumbnail url="http://cdn.phys.org/newman/csz/news/tmb/2013/darkmatter.jpg" width="90" height="90" />
</item>


</channel>
</rss>
